This presentation describes polynomial input preconditioning
for zero-shot time-series forecasting.
The key preliminary is Universal Sequence Preconditioning,
proposed by Marsden and Hazan for online prediction in
marginally stable linear dynamical systems.
Their insight is that instead of asking a learner to infer a
potentially large hidden state directly, one can first
transform the observed sequence with a fixed polynomial
convolution.
Chebyshev-style coefficients are useful because they uniformly
damp the difficult modes of the hidden dynamics across a broad
spectral range.
The intuition for this project is to use that same fixed,
theory-guided signal as information given to a patch-based
transformer before tokenization.
The starting point is a common design in modern time-series
foundation models like Moirai 2.0.
These models split the input sequence into fixed-length
patches, embed each patch independently, and then run a
transformer over the resulting tokens.
This is efficient, but it creates a bottleneck: before
attention, each token only sees its own local patch.
If important structure spans multiple patches, the transformer
has to discover that structure later.
My idea is to expose a small amount of cross-patch information
before tokenization.
I use a fixed polynomial convolution motivated by Universal
Sequence Preconditioning.
In the default setting, the residual channel is r sub t equals
negative x sub t minus thirty two, plus one eighth times x sub
t minus sixty four.
This is computed from the normalized input series, split into
patches, and concatenated alongside the raw input patch and
observation mask.
The only architectural change is that the first projection
layer gets wider, from two patch channels to three.
The transformer decoder, output head, and forecast target are
unchanged.
The overhead is only twelve thousand parameters, or about zero
point one one percent of Moirai 2.0 Small.
This diagram shows the full architectural change.
The orange boxes are the new parts: compute the Chebyshev
residual, optionally apply hint dropout during training,
concatenate the raw input, mask, and residual, and widen the
input projection.
Everything inside the Moirai 2.0 decoder block and the
autoregressive quantile output head stays the same.
The main result is on GIFT-Eval, which has ninety-seven
dataset-by-horizon forecasting configurations.
Across five seeds, the preconditioned model improves
geometric-mean normalized MASE by two point nine percent over
the Moirai 2.0 Small baseline.
After averaging each configuration across seeds, it wins
seventy-two of ninety-seven configurations, with a paired
sign-test p-value below ten to the minus five.
The important control is capacity matching.
I trained the same widened architecture with a zero third
channel and with a duplicate of the input as the third
channel.
Those controls do not reproduce the gain, so the improvement
comes from the polynomial content of the channel.
I also tested whether the result transfers beyond GIFT-Eval.
On FEV-Bench, an independent benchmark with one hundred
forecasting tasks, the same method improves MASE by two point
nine percent and scaled quantile loss by three point one
percent.
In ablations, every tested Chebyshev degree from two through
seven improves over baseline.
Fixed Chebyshev coefficients also outperform learned
coefficient vectors initialized either from Chebyshev
coefficients or from zero.
Finally, the effect grows with training.
At one hundred thousand steps, the MASE improvement reaches
three point nine percent, and the preconditioned model has
lower cross-seed variance than the baseline.
The gains are also largest on longer-horizon forecasting
tasks, where the dropout version is more robust during
autoregressive decoding.
The takeaway is that foundation-model performance does not
only come from scaling model size.
A small, fixed, theory-guided transformation placed before
tokenization can improve zero-shot forecasting while leaving
the transformer itself almost completely unchanged.
For time series models, this suggests a practical path toward
more accurate and parameter-efficient forecasters.